Finding aid for Roy D. Chapin, Jr., Papers, 1928-2001
Bentley Historical Library
Roy D. Chapin, Jr., Papers
1928-2001
Bentley Historical Library
Chapin, Roy Dikeman, 1915-
85103 Aa 2
23.3 linear feet
Chairman of the board and chief executive officer of American Motors Corporation, 1967-1977. Personal correspondence, speeches, papers relating to international business operations of AMC and its divisions, and photographs.
The collection was the gift of Mr. Chapin (donor no. 3584 ) and came to the library in 1979 and 1980. Additional papers came from the family in 2005, and from Horace A. Davis (donor no. 11329 ) in 20September 15 and March 2018.
The collection is open to research.
Roy D. Chapin, Jr., the son of one of the founders of the Hudson Motor Car Company, was born September 21, 1915. After graduation from Yale in 1937, he joined the firm working as an experimental engineer. He expanded his interest in mechanics and worked in key automotive areas in production planning, accounting, manufacturing, car distribution, then in sales administration and field sales, becoming assistant sales manager in 1952.
In 1954, when Hudson and Nash-Kelvinator merged to form the American Motors Corporation, Chapin became assistant treasurer. He became treasurer in 1955 and was elected vice president 1956. That same year he was named executive vice president. In 1960, he was elected executive vice president - international operations. He was elevated to executive vice president and general manager of the automotive division in September 1966. In 1967, he was named chairman and chief executive officer. He served in this capacity until 1977. He remained a member of the board of directors until 1987 when Chrysler acquired the company.
Under his leadership, American Motors prospered, mainly because of its international operation and the success of its compact cars during the period of rising oil prices. In 1970, Chapin was instrumental in purchasing for American Motors the Jeep Corp. from Kaiser Industries. Jeep sales were highly profitable for the company and served to resurrect the market for sports utility vehicles.
Chapin died August 5, 2001.
The collection has been maintained in the following series: Correspondence; Speeches; International file; Automotive topical file; Chairman's files; Travel file; Personal topical file; Visual Materials; Chronological file; and Scrapbook.
Automobile industry and trade -- United States.; Automobile industry.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; American Motors Corporation.; Chapin, Roy Dikeman, 1915-; American Motors Corporation.; Chapin, Roy Dikeman, 1915-; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.
- Correspondence
  - 1942-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1963 (Box 2)
    (1956 missing)
  - 1964-1971 (Box 3)
    (January-March 1969 missing)
  - 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    (October-December 1972 and October-December 1974 missing)
  - Congratulatory letters (General Manager Automotive Division), September 13, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Congratulatory letters (Chairman of the Board, AMC), January 9, 1967 (Box 4)
- Speeches
  - 1958-1967 (Box 5)
  - 1968-1978 (Box 6)
    (no 1972-1973)
- International file
  - Notebook: Advance Program, Automotive International Operations (Box 7)
  - Algeria (Box 7)
  - Argentina (Box 7)
  - Australia (Box 7)
  - Brazil (Box 7)
  - Canada (Box 7)
  - Canada (Box 8)
  - Columbia (Box 8)
  - Costa Rica (Box 8)
  - England (Box 8)
  - France (Box 8)
  - Germany (Box 9)
  - India (Box 9)
  - Iran (Box 9)
  - Israel (Box 9)
  - Italy (Box 9)
  - Japan (Box 9)
  - Japan (Box 10)
  - Korea (Box 10)
  - Lebanon (Box 10)
  - Mexico (Box 10)
  - Monaco (Box 10)
  - Pakistan (Box 10)
  - Peru (Box 10)
  - Philippine Islands (Box 10)
  - Portugal (Box 11)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 11)
  - South Africa (Box 11)
  - Spain (Box 11)
  - Switzerland (Box 11)
  - Thailand (Box 11)
  - Turkey (Box 11)
  - Venezuela (Box 11)
- Automotive topical files
  - Aeroceanic Corporation (Box 11)
  - American Motors Corporation
    - Board of directors materials (Box 11)
    - AMC Headquarters (Box 11)
    - Progress sharing (Box 11)
    - Steering Committee (Box 11)
    - Clippings (Box 11)
  - AMX/III (termination of program) (Box 12)
  - AM General
    - Bus (Box 12)
    - Electric Vehicle (Box 12)
  - Banks (Box 12)
  - Blake, Cassels and Graydon (Box 12)
  - Blue Bird (Box 12)
  - Brown, Boveri and Co. (Box 12)
  - Butler manufacturing (AMG) (Box 12)
  - Centaur (Box 12)
  - Clean Air Act (Sen. Muskie) (Box 12)
  - Commerce Department (Box 12)
  - Concept 80 (Box 12)
  - Curtiss-Wright (Box 12)
  - Electric Car (Box 12)
  - Electric Fuel Propulsion (Aronson) (Box 12)
  - Emissions file (Box 12)
  - Emission Control Information (Box 12)
  - European Financing (Box 12)
  - Gulf and Western Industries, Inc. (Box 12)
  - Gulton Industries, Inc. (Box 12)
  - Guttman, Monroe (Box 12)
  - Hartke, (Sen.) Vance (Box 12)
  - Highway Trust Fund (Box 12)
  - Highway Users Federation for Safety and Mobility (HUFSAM) (Box 13)
  - International Assistant (Box 13)
  - Kaiser Industries (Box 13)
  - Kaiser Stock Sales (Box 13)
  - Knaver, Virginia H (Box 13)
  - LaForce Engine (Box 13)
  - Lear motors (Box 13)
  - Lindberg Ecology Corporation (Box 13)
  - Milwaukee Dual Mode Transit Project (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Model 2121 (Box 13)
  - Morse-Nelson hearings (Box 13)
  - National Business Council for Consumer Affairs (Box 13)
  - National Council on Indian Opportunity (Box 13)
  - Natural Gas Vehicle (Box 13)
  - "Pacer to People", 1975 (Box 13)
  - Phoenix (Box 13)
  - Presidential Task Force on Highway Safety (Box 13)
  - Russia (proposed sales to) (Box 14)
  - Salomon Brothers (Box 14)
  - Select Committee on Small Business (Box 14)
  - Seligman, Eustace (Box 14)
  - Small Car Search (Box 14)
  - Small Car Volumes, 1970-1972 (Box 14)
  - Subaru (Box 14)
  - "T" (Box 14)
  - Transit Bond Proposal (Box 14)
  - Trowbridge, Alexander B (Box 14)
  - Turbines (Box 14)
  - "U-V" (Box 14)
  - U.S. Balance of Payments (Box 14)
  - U.S. Government (Box 14)
  - UMC Industries, Inc. (Box 14)
  - "W" (Box 14)
  - Wankel Engine (Box 14)
  - White Consolidated Industries, Inc. (Box 14)
  - White Motor Company (Box 14)
  - World Energy Conference (Box 15)
  - "X-Y-Z" (Box 15)
- Chairman's files
  - [A-P], 1972-1974 (Box 15)
  - [Q-Z], 1972-1974 (Box 16)
  - [A-Z], 1974 (Box 16)
  - [A-Z], 1975-1978 (Box 17)
  - [A-Z], 1977-1978 (Box 18)
- Travel file
  - 1953-1963 (Box 18)
  - 1964-1974 (Box 18)
- Personal topical files
  - American School in Switzerland (Box 19)
  - Biographical and personal material (Box 19)
  - Boy Scouts of America (Box 19)
  - Chapin, Roy D., III (Box 19)
  - Detroit Science Center (Box 19)
  - Financial (personal), 1956-1963 (Box 19)
    (1958-1961 missing)
  - Foxcroft School (Box 19)
  - Hennepin Property Sale, July 1971 (Box 19)
  - Hudson-Essex Terraplane Owner's Club (Box 19)
  - Industry Policy Advisory Committee (Box 19)
  - International Road Federation (Box 19)
  - Johnson, Pyke (Automotive Safety Foundation) (Box 19)
  - Jolon Valley Vineyards (Box 19)
  - Metamora Shoot (Box 20)
  - Michigan Prairie Chicken Society (Box 20)
  - Miller, Cassidy, Larroca & Lewin (Box 20)
  - New Detroit, Inc. (Box 20)
  - North American Wildlife Federation (Box 20)
  - Ogemaw County Lease Sale, August 1971 (Box 20)
  - Pigeon River Forest (Box 20)
  - Regret letters (Box 20)
  - SEMTA (Southeast Michigan Transportation Authority) (Box 20)
  - Solar Energy Research Institute (SERI) (Box 20)
  - Trout Unlimited (Box 21)
  - United Foundation (Box 21)
  - White House Conference on Highway Safety (Box 21)
  - World Wide Sportsman (Box 21)
  - World Wildlife Fund (Box 21)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (Box 21)
    - Plant opening, Brampton, Ontario, 1961 (Box 21)
    - Plant opening, Argentina, 1961-1962; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - GLAS automobiles (Box 21)
    - Woman with Javelin, 1968 (Box 21)
    - 421 Lakeshore Road, 1965-1966 (Box 21)
  - Film: Nash-Hudson advertisement, 1950s (Box 21)
- Chronological file
  (includes articles by and about Chapin photographs, clippings, AMC annual reports, press releases, memoranda, etc.)
  - 1925-1980, 25 folders (Box 22)
  - 1981-1988, 14 folders (Box 23)
  - 1992 (Box 23)
  - 1994-1997 (Box 23)
  - 2001 (Box 23)
- Scrapbook
  - 1928-1987 (Box 24)
    (includes photographs and newspaper clippings highlighting the career of Roy D. Chapin, Jr.)